Guide to the Engineers Association of ARMA Records WAG.023
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Engineers Association of ARMA Records
1951-1983
WAG.023
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
9.0 linear feet in 9 record cartons.
This collection contains the records of the Engineers Association of ARMA, Local 418 of the International Union of Electrical Workers (IUE), from 1953-1983. This collection documents the unionization of ARMA's Brooklyn Plant of white collar defense engineers and technicians. The collection is made up of minutes and by-laws, office correspondence, the union's publicity and publications, photographs, grievances, arbitrations, and contract agreements and negotiations.
Engineers Association of ARMA.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains the records of the Engineers Association of ARMA, Local 418 of the International Union of Electrical Workers (IUE). The material in the collection spans the entire existence of the union, from 1953-1983. The collection is made up of minutes, constitutions, and by-laws of the union; office correspondence; photographs; and publicity and publications of the union, including newsletters. The unarranged portion of the collection includes contract negotiations and bonus plans for engineers. The unprocessed section also includes labor agreements, including job descriptions, pension plans, health coverage, and contracts. A huge bulk of the unprocessed materials relate to the union's grievances and arbitrations filed with the union's arbitration department, including issues related to security clearance and job descriptions for engineers and technicians. The key issues of arbitration include subcontracting, merit and severance pay, and job descriptions.
The researcher will find in the records of the Engineers Association of ARMA an unusually complete account of the development of a white collar professional union. The collection also gives insights into the work process and labor relations for professionals employed by a defense contractor.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Engineers Association of ARMA (EAA) was founded in March of 1951. Unionization of the plant had begun in 1950 when production employees working at ARMA's Brooklyn Plant became Local 460. The company was founded by Arthur P. Davis in 1918 was and continued to be a defense contractor, initially manufacturing searchlights and, subsequently, fire control systems and gyroscopic equipment for the Navy.
The engineers were compelled to unionize, when the company, to attract professionals during the Korean War labor shortage, paid new engineers as much as senior employees. The engineers decided to form an independent union and on July 11, 1951 the EAA called its first strike. The company had made a settlement with Local 460, and did not see a need to negotiate with the engineers and technicians of ARMA. After a week they were taken seriously by the company. The contract they negotiated provided for a union shop, 25 percent average wage increase, improved benefits, and a model agreement for other engineers, which the EAA had to fight the Wage Stabilization Board and the employer to fulfill. During this period the union helped to form the Engineers and Scientists of America (ESA) which aspired to join engineers nationwide for the purpose of strengthening collective bargaining. (The ARMA engineers later became disenchanted with this organization and withdrew in 1956.)
The expiration of the contracts in 1953 brought the union's bitterest strike. The IUE production local called a strike, and the EAA voted to honor their picket lines. The strike lasted 10 weeks, and some of the engineers were arrested during the first week's violence. After 8 weeks, the production and clerical unions reached a settlement, and the EAA then "officially" went on strike. The other unions honored the EAA picket lines, and a settlement was reached 10 days later.
Again in 1955, when the contract expired, a strike erupted. This time the strike lasted thirteen weeks. After this strike the EAA decided that it would have more influence if it banded together with the other unions in the plant by joining the International Union of Electrical Workers. On February 1, 1956 the ARMA engineers were chartered as IUE Local 418.
The union remained strong and grew in membership from 600 to 1900 as ARMA won defense contracts. ARMA moved its quarters from Bush Terminal to Roosevelt Field, having a total of 6000 employees at its peak of production.
Local 418 successfully negotiated contracts with ARMA with the assistance of their attorney, Stephen Vladeck whom they hired in 1953. He won significant cases for the engineers and technicians of ARMA, including liberalizing the company's policy on security clearance and on admitting female technicians.
Industrial relations improved somewhat, but the union was forced to take strike votes in many of the ensuing contract expiration years because of last minute deadlocked negotiations. The union went on strike for 15 weeks on October 10,1981, mainly because of issues that arose as a result of the merger with United Technologies (see below). The union's fortunes however, were closely tied to the ARMA management which began having problems attracting Pentagon contracts as early as 1953, when the Navy lost confidence in the company's product. The first lay off was in 1959. ARMA was successful in attracting Air Force contracts to produce B.52 tail defense and guidance systems until the middle sixties, after which no further major military contracts were secured. In the 1970's ARMA attracted some private sector work for Lockheed Aircraft, Delta and All Nippon Airlines. ARMA veterans suggest that the company was accustomed to dealing with inflated military budgets and could not compete well in the private market. In 1973 the company was sold to United Technologies and the ARMA division gradually was reduced in size, eventually being closed on October 1, 1983. As a result of this closing, the union was disbanded in October, 1983.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into nine series:
Series I: Union Structure and Organization
Series II: Office Correspondence
Series III: Union Publicity and Publications
Series IV: Labor Agreements
Series V: Arbitrations
Series VI: Grievances and Other Legal Files
Series VII: Contract Negotiations
Series VIII: Job Descriptions
Series IX: Photographs
Materials in Series I-III are arranged alphabetically. Materials in Series IV-IX have not been arranged on the folder level by an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The records of the Engineers Association of ARMA, IUE Local 418 were donated to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Archives by the union in memory of their attorney, Stephen Vladeck in 1983. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1950.187 and 1983.011.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Association of Records Managers and Administrators.; Delta Air Corporation.; Engineers and Scientists of America.; International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers. Local 418 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Lockheed Aircraft Corporation.; United Technologies Corporation.; Vladeck, Stephen C.; Collective labor agreements |z New York (State) |z New York.; Correspondence.; Defense industries |x Employees |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Defense industries |z New York (State) |z New York; Engineers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Publications.; Strikes and lockouts |x Defense industries |z New York (State) |z New York.; White collar workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series I: Union Structure and Organization, 1951-1983
  Scope and Content Note
  Includes constitution and by-laws, minutes of the Representative Council, Executive Board minutes, and membership committee minutes.
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Standard rules, Representive Council (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Representive Council Meetings, includes agendas, minutes, financial reports, correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Representative Council, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Representative Council, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Representative Council, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Representative Council, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Representative Council, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Representative Council, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Representative Council, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Representative Council, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Representative Council, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Representative Council, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Representative Council, 1981 January ? July (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Representative Council, 1981 August ? December (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Representative Council, 1982 January ? July (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Representative Council, 1982 August ? December (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Representative Council, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Executive Board Minutes December, 1951 – November 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Recording Secretary Notes and Minutes of Membership, October 31, 1956 ? September 14, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Membership Minutes, 1955 ? 1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Membership Minutes, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Membership Minutes, 1959 ? 1961 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Membership Minutes, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Membership Minutes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Membership Minutes, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Membership Minutes, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Membership Minutes, 1963 ? 1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Membership Minutes, 1972 ? 1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Membership Minutes, 1977 ? 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Membership Meeting Agendas, 1963 ? 1971 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series II: Office Correspondence, 1953-1969
  Of particular interest are the letters relating to the 1955 strike and ARMA's loss of the Titan Missile contract in 1962.
  - Office Correspondence, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Office Correspondence, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Office Correspondence, 1955 (includes strike material) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Office Correspondence, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Office Correspondence, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Office Correspondence, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Office Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Office Correspondence, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Office Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Office Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Office Correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Vice President to employees regarding the loss of the Titan III contract (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Lay-offs due to loss of Titan Missile contract (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Office Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Office Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Office Correspondence, 196 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Office Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Office Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Office Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Office Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Members Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Members Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Members Correspondence, 1966 ? 1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Members Correspondence, 1969 ? 1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series III: Union Publicity and Publications, 1952-1977
  Includes union press releases; the union's newsletter, Scope and Microscopes; occasional issues of the company's publication, ARMA Magazine; the union's 10th anniversary publication; and bulletins and memoranda.
  - Undated Newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Publicity and News Releases, 1952-1959 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Publicity and News Releases, 1960-1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Memoranda and Bulletins, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Memoranda and Bulletins, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Memoranda and Bulletins, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Memoranda and Bulletins, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Memoranda and Bulletins, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Memoranda and Bulletins, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Memoranda and Bulletins, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Memoranda and Bulletins, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Memoranda and Bulletins, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Weekly fact sheet, 1963 ?1965 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - ARMA Magazine (AE) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scope and Microscope, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scope and Microscope, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Scope and Microscope, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Scope and Microscope, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scope and Microscope, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Scope and Microscope, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Scope and Microscope, Dec 1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Out of Plant Newsletter, 1959-1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Tenth Anniversary Celebration, publication (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Newsletters, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Newsletters, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Newsletters, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Newsletters, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Newsletters, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Newsletters, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Newsletters, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Newsletters, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Newsletters, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Newsletters, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Newsletters, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Newsletters, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Newsletters, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Newsletters, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Newsletters, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Newsletters, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, 1979 (Box 4)
- Series IV: Labor Agreements, 1953-1981 (Box 4)
  Includes pension plans, health coverage, and contracts.
- Series V: Arbitrations, 1954-1981 (Box 6, Box 5)
  This series includes some key issues sent to arbitration including subcontracting, merit and severance pay, and job descriptions.
- Series VI: Grievances and Other Legal Files, 1953-1981 (Box 8, Box 7)
  Some of the key issues sent to arbitration were out of plant service (subcontracting), merit and severance pay, and job descriptions.
- Series VII: Contract Negotiations, 1953-1981 (Box 9)
  Includes union proposals for the "Merit Kitty" or the "Wooded Nickle dispute of 1966," and bonus plans for engineers.
- Series VIII: Job Descriptions, 1953-1981 (Box 9)
  This series includes job descriptions of positions at ARMA, often used in negotiations and arbitrations.
- Series IX: Photographs, 1951-1960 (Box 9)
  This series includes photographic prints of the local's leadership, including portraits of presidents, officers, an unidentified strike scene at ARMA, ARMA corporation building, union office exteriors and meeting places, group portraits, classroom scenes, snapshots of women members, and a cartoon ink drawing.